<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="www.vihari.me/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="www.vihari.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="www.vihari.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-02-06T21:47:50-08:00</updated><id>www.vihari.me//</id><title type="html">Vihari Muttineni</title><subtitle>Student at Cal Poly studying Computer Science. I like programming, photography, and writing. The goal is to update this blog at least once a week.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Happiness and Control</title><link href="www.vihari.me/jekyll/update/2017/02/06/happiness-and-control.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happiness and Control" /><published>2017-02-06T20:13:41-08:00</published><updated>2017-02-06T20:13:41-08:00</updated><id>www.vihari.me/jekyll/update/2017/02/06/happiness-and-control</id><content type="html" xml:base="www.vihari.me/jekyll/update/2017/02/06/happiness-and-control.html">&lt;p&gt;The other day, my British Literature professor likened going to the bars and going to Church as more or less the same thing. He argued that when you go to Church, you want to experience spirituality by praying to God, and that when you go to the bars you want to experience a pause from sobriety – but it is that desire to experience change that is constant. He continued on to explain that people only do things because they desire change, and that if you boil down all human decision making, it comes down to a decision made either in fear or in desire. 
Incidentally, George Soros agrees with him, so I think my professor is in good company. Soros once said (this is paraphrased) that: “the only two motivators to make money is either fear or greed (desire). I grew up in abject poverty, and I am so deeply scared of being poor again that I will forever try to make more money”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fear or desire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we make decisions every single day, and every single one of those decisions come from either fear of x, or desire for y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, does it even matter if your decisions are driven by fear or by desire? They both sound bad (where is ~logic~?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that it does. In freshman year I took a class called Multicultural Living in America. It was through the Kinesiology department, and it was 10 weeks where I learned about the impacts of cultural upbringing and socioeconomic factors on human health. The single biggest takeaway hammered into our heads was that stress -&amp;gt; elevated cortisol production -&amp;gt; you die young after heart and other cardiovascular complications. Cortisol is the hormone most attributed to your fight-or-flight adrenaline-infused mode, and it turns out that the human body can’t take too many doses of that drug. The class was a massive case study on white people vs. black people, and the second biggest takeaway was that the reason black people die younger than white people (across the board, adjusted for other reasons, very statistically significantly) is because they are experiencing more stress because they feel less in control of their lives. [1] It’s not just the more stress -&amp;gt; cortisol -&amp;gt; death at a younger age chain-of-events that is troubling though, because the feeling less in control actually brings a whole host of problems. We spent a couple lectures in that class learning about anxiety, depression, eating disorders, chronic fatigue, and a whole host of other problems that feeling less in control begets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you die young, but before you die young, your life sucks. You’re sub-optimal mentally, you’re having less deeply restorative sleep (and less of it) so you’re tired all the time and sub-optimal physically, and it has even been proven to reduce optimism. All because you don’t feel in control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems so simple. Take back control, and you’ll live a great life! You’ll be happy and energetic and hopeful and best of all, you’ll live a long life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you do it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can start (and it really is only just a start) by examining again the dichotomy my literature professor explained. He argued that all the decisions we make in life are governed by either fear or desire, and he set it up as a mutually exclusive statement (that is – a decision is made either in fear, or in desire). He’s right, but it turns out that fear and desire are just two halves of the same exact coin – and that any decision made in fear can just as equally be made in desire (and actually IS, and we just have to acknowledge that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing. We react to external stimuli badly. A professor assigns a test (oh man, I have to study). A professor schedules a senior project meeting (I have to go to campus). A boyfriend or girlfriend gives you an ultimatum in an argument (I have to compromise)! In all of these situations, we see someone doing something TO us, and that mental frame-of-mind of someone else doing something to us takes the control and power out of our own hands. When you feel like you don’t have control and power, suddenly all the bad things happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First a disclaimer: it is impossible to avoid these situations. Even if you’re not in college and have never been in a relationship, there are code reviews in industry, managers, friends, utilities to pay, or some guy in line at the bus stop who shoves you. Forget trying to get control back by eliminating situations where you interact with other people and where they do things TO you. It is also not a good idea to try to wall yourself off from getting hurt by becoming emotionally unattached/unavailable – no man is an island and the cracks will show up eventually and you’ll be back to square one (believe me on this one – I once tried).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now think about decisions that you’ve made that have come out of desire. Starting taking singing lessons because I wanted to sing. Started cooking at home because I wanted to be healthy. Stopped cooking at home because I wanted to be lazy. Reaching out to a friend because I wanted to reconnect with them. Intentionally letting a call go to voicemail because I didn’t want to ruin my flow as I was typing this blog post. All of these decisions gave me pleasure and happiness, because they were all in my control and I desired something. They were internally driven decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look back at all the examples where other people do stuff TO us. Those are stressful, and whatever decision we made (studying, going to school, accepting an ultimatum, etc.) were all done out of fear/lack of control, and we overall feel not-good. Those are all externally driven decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So decisions made out of fear are decisions that are externally driven (people doing stuff TO us), and decisions made out of desire are internally driven (I want something).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer isn’t to change a single thing about your lifestyle. It’s only to change how you process the external stimuli (and to continually be thoughtful).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take the studying example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I think I'm studying for the test because I have to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;i&gt;But why do I have to?&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Well it's because I am afraid of failing the class if I don't. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;i&gt;But why am I afraid of failing the class?&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because I'm afraid of not getting my degree if I don't.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Why am I afraid of that?&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because I am afraid of not living up to my parent's expectations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Why?&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because I look up to my parents and I am afraid of their disappointment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can go as far down this rabbit hole as you want, and you can for any of the externally-driven, stressful situations/decisions, and you’ll find that there’s a chain of fear/lack of control that culminates in a decision made grudgingly, unhappily, and adding to your cortisol production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people here say, “Just drop out!” but as I explained above, avoiding situations where people do things TO you is impossible because those situations will always exist, so let’s try something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fear and desire are two halves of the same coin, so lets just apply desire to the same situation (and come back up the rabbit hole).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;I look up to my parents and I want their approval.&lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;I want to live up to my parents’ expectations by getting a degree from a university.&lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;I want to get a get a degree from a university by passing all the required classes.&lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;I want to pass this required class by studying for my test. &lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;Oh. That's why I'm studying for this test.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems a little silly that all it takes is you telling yourself that you’re doing something because you “want” to do it instead of you “have” to do it, but I promise it works. Ever since my professor mentioned this concept of all decisions are made as a desire for change and all change is motivated by either desire or fear, I’ve been actively trying to remind myself that everything I do, I do because I want to do it and not because someone is forcing me to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This works for big things like code reviews for my senior project but also little things like my roommate telling me to take the trash out (I want to do it because I want to maintain the integrity of the chore chart because I want to invest in our great roommate dynamic because I want to preserve my quality-of-life).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a lot happier since I’ve started internalizing external things people do TO me (note though that you really have to constantly think and reflect on why you WANT to be doing something, because sometimes the deeper meaning that actually provides control and peace isn’t immediately self-evident – so it can be exhausting at times to search your brain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So take back happiness, by taking back control over every single decision in your life (and you don’t even have to change anything about the way you live!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] 
It is important to note here that black people across America aren’t just mysteriously and magically feeling “out of control” without justification; there are actually a large number of reasons why they consistently feel this way ranging from volume levels of surroundings while trying to sleep (denser housing units) to the shortage of grocery stores and abundance of fast food restaurants in neighborhoods with primary black communities (harder to feed your children balanced meals), etc. If you are more interested in this, I still have my textbooks from freshman year from this class.&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">The other day, my British Literature professor likened going to the bars and going to Church as more or less the same thing. He argued that when you go to Church, you want to experience spirituality by praying to God, and that when you go to the bars you want to experience a pause from sobriety – but it is that desire to experience change that is constant. He continued on to explain that people only do things because they desire change, and that if you boil down all human decision making, it comes down to a decision made either in fear or in desire. 
Incidentally, George Soros agrees with him, so I think my professor is in good company. Soros once said (this is paraphrased) that: “the only two motivators to make money is either fear or greed (desire). I grew up in abject poverty, and I am so deeply scared of being poor again that I will forever try to make more money”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Homogeneity Breeds Feedback Loops But Mass Brings Homogeneity</title><link href="www.vihari.me/jekyll/update/2017/01/29/homogeneity-breeds-feedback-loops-but-mass-breeds-homogeneity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Homogeneity Breeds Feedback Loops But Mass Brings Homogeneity" /><published>2017-01-29T04:13:41-08:00</published><updated>2017-01-29T04:13:41-08:00</updated><id>www.vihari.me/jekyll/update/2017/01/29/homogeneity-breeds-feedback-loops-but-mass-breeds-homogeneity</id><content type="html" xml:base="www.vihari.me/jekyll/update/2017/01/29/homogeneity-breeds-feedback-loops-but-mass-breeds-homogeneity.html">&lt;p&gt;“The three things you don’t talk about in polite conversation are money, religion, and politics.” Why is this something that we hear growing up? Because you can never be sure what someone’s position on money, religion, and politics are – and because nobody likes friction. Because humans have empathy, we tend to want everyone else in a group to feel comfortable and at ease, and it is infinitely easier for someone to feel comfortable when they can relate to the topic of the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is, it isn’t just money, religion, and politics that we don’t talk about. We don’t talk about a whole boatload of things all the time and it’s detrimental to us all, and I’ve only recently been realizing this. Let me illustrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to take a circle in space, and fill it in with an abstract representation of myself. Every decision, every opinion, every thought, interest, passion, curiosity, etc. When I am alone (or more technically, in a group of 1 – myself), I am accountable only to myself, and I am 100% unadulterated. My abstract circle hanging over myself and my real self are one and the same, and the amount of time I spend doing things and thinking about things very accurately reflect my inner model of who I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/vihari.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vihari&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, take Rishab. He walks into the room, and he has his own abstract representation of himself hanging over himself as well. Every decision, every opinion, every thought… etc. Please note that there is some overlap!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/vihari_and_rishab.png&quot; alt=&quot;Vihari And Rishab&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now in an ideal world, the abstract group of two that has just formed (me and Rishab) becomes the union of the abstract representation of me and the abstract representation of Rishab, and our group would now equally do stuff and think about everything from the superset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/union.png&quot; alt=&quot;Union&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In actuality though, because humans in groups are hardwired to make each other feel at ease, what happen is that we focus on how we are alike – at the detriment to how we are not-alike. In other words, the group of Rishab and I becomes the intersection of Rishab and Vihari, not the union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/intersection.png&quot; alt=&quot;Intersection&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see this clearly every day I interact with Rishab. I love Indian music, he hates it. So I don’t play Indian music around him (he literally tells my Alexa to shut up). He’s really big into watching “great movies”, I am not a huge movie person. We don’t really watch movies together all that often. Instead, we focus on what we both like (and know that the other likes): startups, introspection, competition for self-improvement, programming, good beer, programming while drinking good beer, and The Avengers (although Tony Stark is my idol and Captain America is his so we argue here too…) But whenever Rishab is in a group with me, he can’t sing along at the top of his lungs to the Moana soundtrack on Spotify (yes this happens regularly when he’s in the shower, no I don’t know why I’m still okay living with him in SF), and he only gives me a five minute attention span to say whatever I want to say about photography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The examples I’ve brought up are lighthearted and the argument can be made that they don’t really matter, but that’s because Rishab and I are actually painfully similar where it matters (painful for my ego). Let’s go back to the visuals though, and take a look at another group that we’re both part of: the Bae Area Hackers Facebook Messenger group. This is a group of 7 close friends in the Cal Poly CS department who have gone through years of courses together, and we’re all fairly tight. There won’t be more than a couple hours until someone messages in this chat on any given day, so it’s safe to say I’m pretty good friends with all of these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/bae_area_plain.png&quot; alt=&quot;plain&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would think that close friends will talk about everything, but as it turns out, the Bae Area Hackers group talks almost exclusively about: classes and coursework, Silicon Valley and the latest HackerNews updates, Trump, and occasionally our accomplishments in a congratulatory way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well this is weird. Colton is in a band that has literally played in front of thousands of people by now, but he almost never mentions it. Brad’s a phenomenally good snowboarder who regularly keeps up with articles/posts/videos but I never knew he did that until I asked him for an example for this specific post – I thought he just went every winter sometimes and that was that. Caleb has been working and living in the city for months now and I know nothing about his life there. Why aren’t we talking about any of this stuff? For that matter, why have I never mentioned photography in the group? I’m basically obsessed with photography right now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s because I can’t relate to Colton and his band. I don’t know the first thing about musical instruments, and neither does Rishab or Mitch. Caleb doesn’t bring the city life up mostly because he’s too cool and busy for us now – Caleb if you’re reading this like you’re “reading” all the messages in the group chat can you seriously just say something…anything :(. And Brad sees no reason to talk about snowboarding to “California Snowboarders” (read: I can make s-turns down green circles and some easier blue squares.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing. Colton could talk to us about his band, and we wouldn’t mind. Brad could link us to whatever cool thing is happening in the pro snowboarding scene he follows, and we’d have moderate interest in it. I could talk to the group about photography and whatever new technique I’m picking up (going into perspective shots next!), but even if it is infinitesimally easier to talk about something that I know everyone relates to, then chances are I will bring that topic up instead (and so will everyone else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, it would be a glorious time to be alive if the Bae Area Hackers was the union of all 7 of us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/bae_area_union.png&quot; alt=&quot;bae_union&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it’s the intersection, and that’s bad! Suddenly, we don’t have much to talk about at all, and we just keep talking about that stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/bae_area_intersection.png&quot; alt=&quot;bae_intersection&quot; class=&quot;center-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, homogeneity leads to feedback loops. This makes sense. Because humans are inherently empathetic and want as many group members as possible to feel at ease and comfortable, we willingly sacrifice our non-conformist and minority viewpoints/ideals/topics/experiences (in the current context of whatever group we’re in) in a very noble effort to be kind to each other, but now that group is stuck in a not very mentally stimulating feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you break that? The prevailing logic to breaking feedback loops is to add different input. Let’s try that by continuing our case study on the Bae Area Hackers group. We’ve never discussed feminism, so let’s add a friend who really believes in that and knows a lot about that. I think my life would also be enriched if everyone in the group wasn’t a techie, so let’s add some liberal arts majors and business majors (or even some other type of engineering – not that I know the first thing about engineering tbh). Rishab would probably want to learn more about underwater basketweaving or something like that, so we’ll add someone who is an expert at that where that is their primary hobby in life. We should probably add girls too, because they will add a great viewpoint to our discussions we are probably lacking. We should also add people above and below our grade, because otherwise we’re too insulated. Probably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was our problem? The Bae Area Hackers was too homogeneous, so we added more to the group (we probably should come up with a new name now too…) until we “fixed the problem”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But remember my point from earlier? A group does not become the union of its members, but the intersection. You want to know what the intersection is between 1) a bunch of tech bros and 2) liberal arts majors and 3) underwater basketweaving and 4) girls and 5) guys and 6) an aerospace engineer and 7) a freshmen and 8) someone that graduated two years out? Things like Beyoncé. The Golden State Warriors. Donald Trump. “Just Google It.” Memes. Whatever Will Smith’s kid tweets next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rishab actually thinks Beyoncé is overrated though. That’s just him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is very little I would actually like to talk about in this hypothetical group that would not make at least some people feel left out because they can’t relate to it. And the same goes for every single other person in the group, so in the end we make polite conversation that is banal and dull and ever-so-meaningless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our parents told us not to talk about religion, money, and politics. Don’t worry Pops, I don’t talk about anything really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that we didn’t understand the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought the Bae Area Hackers group was too homogeneous, and we did “the right thing” by diversifying it. The thing is, the things we were talking about were too homogeneous, not the composition of the group. And although the composition of the group does get fixed by adding more people, you are actually making the topics of conversation even more homogeneous because even more things have now become minority viewpoints or non-conformist to this new group’s composition. I can’t even talk about Stripe anymore (and these boys know I talk about Stripe wayyyyy too much). By trying to solve a problem, we actually made it worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how does a group stop being too homogeneous? The quickest, fastest, easiest way is to actually make the group smaller, because as you take people out of a group, the intersection of the people remaining gets that much larger and people are comfortable talking about more stuff. I’m sure you guys have had times when you’ll hang out with a subset of a clique you’re a part of and all of a sudden you feel like you have connected with them on a much deeper level – well it’s because you have! You will always have more in common with one person than you do with two, and more in common with two than with three, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is harder. Members of the group need to both A) actively offer up non-conformist opinions, thoughts, and ideas, and B) actively support and inquire about other group members’ non-conformist opinions, thoughts, and ideas. I need to convince Colton that I care about hearing the latest news from his band just as much as I want to hear about whatever Apple does next, and I need to let Mitch know that yeah, you should bring your girlfriend up sometimes because we’d like to hear it. Maybe the group could give you decent advice about that too instead of just about career fairs and the Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homogeneity-in-expression of a group leads to feedback loops, but mass in composition of a group leads to even more homogeneity-in-expression. Adding people to a group almost always reduces the variation of expression that the group has, just because we are so empathetic and considerate of one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s really shocking to say this, but I think I would have more to comfortably talk about to any stranger I meet at a coffeeshop than fifteen of my closest friends all put together. The faster we realize that fixing expression in a group has nothing to do with adding more voices, but listening more to the voices already present, the faster we’ll be able to really learn from each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the noble thing to do is to go to my large groups and have everyone deal with their uncomfortability and awkwardness and have people bring up things that not everyone can relate to. That may be the better of the two options, and maybe some day I will do it, but for now I think I’m just going to go with the easier route and just spend more time with small groups of people at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scattered final thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I never spent any time alone, and I think I would like to change that. I have realized that it is impossible to be 100% yourself while around anyone else, and I want to figure out who I am.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The whole point to clubs and social groups is to bring like-minded people together to celebrate doing niche things. Clubs are the closest you'll get to being able to express your minority interests in a social atmosphere (Chess Club, Math Club, Photography Club, Sailing Club, Off-Roading Club, etc).
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everyone you hang out with has myriads of fascinating interests that they suppress because it is more polite to talk about what everyone can relate to. If you care, ask about those interests (note: I care!)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;As usual, if you disagree with anything, feel free to message me and we can talk about it! I’m sure I’m wrong about some things that I wrote about, and even if not, just getting another lens/frame-of-reference to look at the same topics will always be helpful and eye-opening.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">“The three things you don’t talk about in polite conversation are money, religion, and politics.” Why is this something that we hear growing up? Because you can never be sure what someone’s position on money, religion, and politics are – and because nobody likes friction. Because humans have empathy, we tend to want everyone else in a group to feel comfortable and at ease, and it is infinitely easier for someone to feel comfortable when they can relate to the topic of the conversation.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I Post Relentlessly on Snapchat (Stories)</title><link href="www.vihari.me/jekyll/update/2017/01/23/why-i-post-relentlessly-on-Snapchat(Stories).html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I Post Relentlessly on Snapchat (Stories)" /><published>2017-01-23T20:13:41-08:00</published><updated>2017-01-23T20:13:41-08:00</updated><id>www.vihari.me/jekyll/update/2017/01/23/why-i-post-relentlessly-on-Snapchat(Stories)</id><content type="html" xml:base="www.vihari.me/jekyll/update/2017/01/23/why-i-post-relentlessly-on-Snapchat(Stories).html">&lt;p&gt;First, a few stories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, a friend I haven’t talked to in over three months commented on one of my Stories with a bit of advice (I had used a mirror as a bounce light for a portrait photography shot, and he recommended that I try a white poster board instead as the mirror will in most cases actually reflect too much light – he was right).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran into a friend at the bars a couple weeks ago, and the first thing that came out of her mouth was: “I love your Snapchat Stories so much. They make me feel like I still know your life”. She was one of my closest friends freshman year, but we don’t talk much anymore. More on this later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Saturday night a friend I hadn’t seen in ages ambled into my living room around midnight (I had stayed in that night) and almost immediately launched into a monologue: “Vihari I want you to know that I appreciate your book review Stories so much. I wish I could bookmark them and look at them later when I’m deciding which book to read next. I also miss you. I haven’t seen you anywhere near as often as I’d like, and that’s not because I’m too busy or anything, but I just am not putting in the effort and  to be honest that won’t change so I’m not even going to say we should hang out more often because it won’t happen. But I value you as a person and I love keeping up with your life while I’m taking a shit in the morning, so thank you for posting so many interesting stories”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had people message me recommendations of their favorite books, invite themselves over to check out some new thing I posted about (like my projector) or join me at the library when they see that I’m there, and I’ve had people I haven’t talked to in ages ask me for book recommendations because they wanted to start reading again. All of this by the way, has been completely unsolicited (but definitely not unwanted)! I just post stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why do I do it, and why do I do it so much?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is three-part: transparency, connection, and inspiration/social-capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s do transparency first. Many years ago, I was empty. I had zero substance through all of high school, and I was the ultimate chameleon. I had a half-decent ability to read situations and people, and I used that to basically reflect people back to themselves, which gave me a fairly disjointed and confusing set of cliques that I ~sort-of-belonged-in~. Then, I realized I had a half-decent ability to read situations and people, and I decided I wanted to see how far I could take it. Stupid, I know. So I started lying. I pretended to be someone I wasn’t to one person, and then turned around and pretended to be someone else that I still wasn’t to someone else, and in between all of these facades and context switches, I lost what little personality I had ever had. I was purely reactive, just giving everyone whatever version of ‘Vihari’ I decided they wanted to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever continual micro-highs and blips of validation I got were vastly dwarfed by demoralizing exhaustion. It’s not fun being fake, but I kept going, because that’s what addicts do, and I was addicted to the rush I got when I gave people exactly who they wanted to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a close family friend growing up, many of you know him. His name is Teja and he hated my shenanigans. When we both submitted our intent to come to Cal Poly, we requested to be roommates, and he told me uncompromisingly that if I tried to pull the same games in college, he would publically oust me. Be yourself, he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you look back on your life 20, 30, 40 years out, only a few moments remain in your memory. That day will be one of them, and I am thankful for Teja’s intervention to this day. This sounds entirely out of a YA novel, but I didn’t tell a single lie for the first several months of college, because I wanted to try that out. It was every bit as refreshing and exhilarating as being fake was exhausting and demoralizing. It was fun. I was having fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alcoholics never say “I’m not an alcoholic anymore.” They say “I’ve been sober for x days/months/years”. I met a friend’s dad once who said “I’ve been sober for 15 years”. It’s because addicts never ever really stop being addicts, they just learn to control themselves so they don’t hurt those around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What freed me from the shackles of continual facades was being extremely forthright about who I was, and displaying that in as large a medium as I possibly can for accountability’s sake. In freshman year, I just told everyone everything I could, but Snapchat has saved me so much time and effort with their Snapchat Stories. It forces me to stay accountable to everyone else. I can’t make up fun/cool/interesting things that I’ve done to on-the-spot relate to someone, because at this point if I say I did something and it wasn’t on my Snapchat Story, literally probably nobody would believe me (and they shouldn’t!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snapchat Storying everything I do frees me to just be myself, because it forces transparency and then, when I know that I can’t impress everyone and I CAN’T please everyone, it allows me to define myself however I’d like and really pursue those things (I am currently going through a reading and photography phase – but you already knew that). Maybe someday I will be at a point in my life where I trust myself to not instinctively, reactively play Simon Says with people and maybe that day has already come, but I’m not willing to risk relapsing just yet. So the Stories and very public transparency will continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason I Story my entire life is for connection. A rolling rock collects no moss, and in the same way, it takes a lot less fuel to continue a relationship than it takes to rekindle a dead one. I know, I’ve tried. Once you haven’t talked to someone in several months or a year or two, they just generally are not willing to put in the effort to restart a friendship (to Madeleine Han, who reached out to me out of the blue and basically told me “we’re going to be friends again”, I salute you – and am honored). But it is so much more fluid to just converse semi-regularly, and Snapchat Stories is again, an incredible medium. First of all, it’s opt-in (so I never feel like I’m forcing my life on anyone who is clearly disinterested, because then they wouldn’t take the effort to watch it), and secondly, because it is so ephemeral and pictorial, it allows for very concise communication of information that I don’t have to look at with the lens of the test of time, which again, allows for breathtaking honesty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of these two very liberating factors, I allow myself to post a very diverse array of life snapshots, and different people comment on different pictures. That’s what I love! People often talk about the 80-20 rule, and sure, it does pop up in a lot of places, but if I were to map the number of times people have commented on certain stories, it’s a fairly uniform random distribution. Pictures of a roommate drinking, a picture of a surfboard at a beach, a book, a trash can in an emergency room I thought had a cool color, it doesn’t matter what I post, someone will react to it strongly. And that’s awesome, because it means I’ve built up a set of really great, different viewpoints (people) in my life. Every single time someone Snapchat Chats me about a Story or mentions it to me when I run into them at the grocery store or on campus, I am grateful that I posted it because it means that I have helped keep my bond alive with that person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s a really reductive viewpoint to say that you will be friends with everyone you need to be friends with, or that you’ll make time for the people who are important. I’ve lost too many friends I’ve deeply valued to the combination of sheer laziness and procrastination (“oh I’ll see them next week”), and I miss them all. I reference you to &lt;a href=&quot;http://zenpencils.com/comic/93-charles-hanson-towne-around-the-corner/&quot;&gt;this very sad comic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have met and become friends with many fascinating, great people in my life. They matter to me. If Snapchat Storying allows me to stay connected with even one friend that I otherwise would have lost touch with, I’ll gladly take the hazing other people give me about “how boring my stories are”. There are just so many people I genuinely care about that I can’t see as often as I’d like to, and I don’t want to lose them any more than I already have by virtue of time. So please comment on my surf trip, my basic meal at Taco Bell, or tell me that you disagree about the color of Rishab’s shirt, and do it on your own time (like my friend in the bathroom during the morning). I will respond every single time, because we’re all in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://waitbutwhy.com/2015/12/the-tail-end.html&quot;&gt;tail end of our relationships&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final reason I Snapchat is to build social-capital. There’s a buzzword floating around Silicon Valley lately about ‘recommendation-graphs’. The idea is that you are a single point in a densely connected graph, with lines connecting you to all of the other people you interact with, and you and your graph is surrounded by all the noise in the world – every YouTube video, every blog post and podcast, every New York Times Bestseller, every bit of consumable media out there. It’s the role of your recommendation graph to suggest content that would otherwise pass through in the endless noise, by virtue of a strong signal. For example, when Rishab sends me the previously linked &lt;i&gt;WaitButWhy&lt;/i&gt; article called &lt;i&gt;The Tail End&lt;/i&gt;, or Christopher McWilliams tells me to read &lt;i&gt;Infinite Jest&lt;/i&gt; as my next book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are all my recommendation graph, but you need to know what I even want to see before you pass it along. Nobody recommended books for me to read until I started publically Storying that I’m really into reading again, and all of a sudden I’ve got at least 5 recommendations I’ll make my way through. People who knew really cool photography tips and tricks never would have told me if I hadn’t displayed my desire to learn to better myself by snapchatting that I was watching a lecture series on photography over winter break. But it’s not enough, I think, to just tell people once “I’m into reading”, or “I’m into photography”. Because something fascinating has been happening in the last couple weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a really quick aside. This is not at all about people I interact with in person on a regular basis. They already know my life, and they already have other mediums of communication with me. I’m extolling the greatness of Snapchat as a lightweight and on-your-own-time medium to keep up with people you don’t see face-to-face on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to something fascinating: people I haven’t talked to in forever have asked me for books to read, books I highly recommend because they want to “get back into reading”. People I don’t interact with on a regular basis send me pictures they’ve taken and ask for critique, and I do my best to help them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s happening here? I don’t presume to know exactly, but here’s my best guess:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often say that you’re the average of your five closest friends. I don’t know if I believe that anymore in our hyperconnected and extremely social-media heavy day and age, but what I do believe is that people take their cues from the people they surround themselves with and observe on a regular basis. If someone who regularly sees me Snapchat Story books I’ve read, they are prompted to maybe read themselves, because it has been brought back into the front of their mind. This foreground/background of the mind discussion has been beaten to death I think (for example, the age-old adage: “out of sight, out of mind”), but Tim Urban has an extremely &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/tim_urban_inside_the_mind_of_a_master_procrastinator&quot;&gt;eye-opening way of looking at procrastination&lt;/a&gt; that I think everyone should watch if they’ve ever found themselves in a situation where they put stuff off indefinitely (I don’t want to take any astonishment out of his talk so I won’t say any more than this, but this was one of the most important videos of my life)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am nothing without my vast recommendation graph. Some edges in my graph are bidirectional (you guys!), but many are unidirectional (Twitter accounts of notable thinkers in Silicon Valley, books I have read from famous authors, etc). It’s the bidirectional edges that have the most room for growth, because those people know me and understand me as a person, and so can most effectively recommend things to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that me relentlessly posting the books I have read, the pictures I’ve taken, the hobbies I am interested in and the articles I have read inspires other people to pursue their own non-conventional hobbies with more rigor, and that can only benefit the entire recommendation graph because over time, the conversations we have and the things they link me to and recommend will be more and more intellectually stimulating, and we will all become better people for it. As a concrete example, if my posting books that I read has inspired even one person to pick up reading again (which I know it has), and that person reads a brilliant book and recommends it back to me that I never would have chanced upon, then all of this will have been worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot filter out all the noise in the world by myself, and decide what is great and worth reading and what isn’t. A friend tried to read the economist cover-to-cover; he quit within a couple weeks. That’s a single magazine. How on Earth am I ever going to even know what will help me develop into the best person I can be? Recommendations from people who know me well, and have been consuming content themselves. So: recommendation graphs; because social capital. And by publically and unapologetically announcing things like cooking at home, reading books, staying up late to finish a blog post for fun (3:45 AM), or even just catching up with an old friend, I am inspiring at least some of you to also tackle the things you’d like to tackle in your lives, and that will feedback loop back into making me a better person as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Godspeed to us all, and don’t be a stranger!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To summarize:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I post relentlessly because it keeps me honest (and as a corollary, frees me to really be me)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I post relentlessly because it allows me to ameliorate the negative effects on relationships time-spent-without has.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I post relentlessly because I have been inspiring at least some people to do that extra one thing they've been meaning to do, and I enjoy seeing people grow and knowing I have played at least a trivial role in their determination/resoluteness. 
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final Thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;If you've made it this far, I don't care if we haven't talked in ages, please message me and say hi.&lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;If you have any disagreements with anything I said while you were reading it, feel free to message me about that too! I am not arrogant enough to think that I am 100% right, or even mostly right, and I would appreciate any insight you can provide to sway my views.&lt;/li&gt;
   &lt;li&gt;I will never turn down a book recommendation, and if you think I'll benefit from reading a great article, send that my way too!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;
“We human beings are social beings. We come into the world as the result of others’ actions. We survive here in dependence on others. Whether we like it or not, there is hardly a moment of our lives when we do not benefit from others’ activities. For this reason, it is hardly surprising that most of our happiness arises in the context of our relationships with others.”
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
-Dalai Lama&lt;/p&gt;</content><summary type="html">First, a few stories:</summary></entry></feed>
